Good morning, I'm Dan Maryles and I'm filling in for Rabbi Lenzner
while he's away, and today's דף daf is בבא מציעא Bava Metzia
צ"ה tzadik hey 95, it is the first day of טבת, Tevet,
it's ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, it is חנוכה, Chanukah, it's December 30th.
And we are going to pick up from towards the bottom of
צ"ד עמוד ב tzadik daled amud bet actually, just to get us
caught up with a little bit of context. So we had been
discussing where do we learn some of the פטורים p'turim or how
can we learn that a שואל, shoel, of someone who borrows something
is פטור patur in a case of בעליו עמו, ba'alav imo, the
owner is there working alongside with the person borrowing the object, and
how is that can be contrasted, how do we contrast the obligations
or the liabilities of a שואל shoel with those of a שומר
שכר, shomer sachar, someone who is paid to watch something but does
not have permission to use it. And what came up here is
a מחלוקת machloket between Rabbi יאשיה Yoshiyah and Rabbi יונתן Yonatan in
a ברייתא braita about how we can make certain kinds of דרשות
drashot because what we were talking about is whether or not the
liabilities
of a שואל shoel would extend to a case of שבויה, shvuyah,
the animal was captured. So the ברייתא braita says, דתניא d'tanya the
third to last line in צ"ד עמוד ב, tzadik daled amud bet,
איש אשר יקלל את אביו ואת אמו,
ish asher yekallel et aviv
ve'et imo, so if in the פסוק pasuk refers to a person
who would curse either of his parents, את אביו ואת אמו, et
aviv ve'et imo, אין לי אלא אביו ואמו, ein li ela aviv
ve'imo,
but it sounds like it might mean only both parents. You have
to curse both parents in order to be liable. Okay, אביו בלא
אמו אמו בלא אביו מניין, aviv belo imo, imo belo aviv minayin,
how do I know that even if you curse only one parent
you're also going to be liable
מניין? minayin? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, אביו ואמו קלל אביו קלל אמו
קלל. aviv ve'imo killel, aviv killel imo killel. So because the פסוק
pasuk at various places places each parent next to the word קלל,
killel, so that provides a source that each of them independently not
both together. דברי Divrei Rabbi יאשיה. Yoshiya. That's Rabbi יאשיה Yoshiyah's interpretation.
Rabbi יונתן Yonatan agrees to the הלכה halacha but he disagrees about
what the דרשה drasha is. Rabbi יונתן Yonatan אומר, omer, משמע שניהם
כאחד ומשמע אחד בפני עצמו. mashma shneihem ke'echad umashma echad bifnei atzmo.
It makes sense that both of them, it could either refer to
שניהם כאחד, shneihem ke'echad,
both of them together, or one by him or herself, עד שיפרוט
לך הכתוב יחדיו, ad sheyifrot lecha hakatuv yachdav,
until the פסוק pasuk is explicit that יחדיו, yachdav, that they're together.
רש"י Rashi points out the example is כמו שפרט לך הכתוב בחורש
שור וחמור, k'mo sheperet lecha hakatuv bechoreish shor vachamor, plowing with a
donkey and an ox יחדיו. yachdav. Because obviously or maybe not obviously,
the Torah if it had left out the word יחדיו, yachdav, if
the פסוק pasuk had just said לא יחרוש בשור וחמור, lo yacharosh
b'shor vachamor, so
okay, I'm not allowed to plow with either an ox or a
donkey. So the fact that the פסוק pasuk has to include the
word יחדיו yachdav to tell me that it means both animals together
and not one or the other, so that's what Rabbi יונתן Yonatan
thinks. And therefore איש אביו ואמו, ish aviv ve'imo, איש אשר יקלל
את אביו ואת אמו, ish asher yekallel et aviv ve'et imo,
so it doesn't say יחדיו yachdav together, and that's why it would
either be one or the other separately.
An interesting point I saw in the ריטב"א Ritva quoting from someone
we don't hear from so often, it's Rabbi פנחס הלוי. Pinchas Halevi.
Rabbi פנחס הלוי Pinchas Halevi is the brother of the רא"ה, Ra'ah,
who is now I think widely believed to have been the author
of the ספר החינוך. Sefer Hachinuch. For a long time people thought
the רא"ה Ra'ah wrote ספר החינוך Sefer Hachinuch but it sort of
seems not to make sense because he contradicts things that we know
that the רא"ה Ra'ah held, so it may be Rabbi פנחס הלוי
Pinchas Halevi his brother. So here he says that this principle about
יחדיו yachdav could only apply to מצוות לא תעשה. mitzvot lo ta'aseh.
Because obviously something like a מצוות עשה mitzvot asei like taking the
ד' מינים... daled minim...
so taking the ד' מינים daled minim would be something that obviously
you have to take all four together. It couldn't make sense that
if the Torah didn't mention the word יחדיו yachdav you would only
have to take one. So we're on the top of צ"ה עמוד
א. tzadik hey amud alef.
So that's Rabbi יונתן Yonatan's position. Rabbi יאשיה Yoshiya does not think
you need יחדיו yachdav together and Rabbi יונתן Yonatan thinks you do.
So אפילו תימא רבי יאשיה לחלק הכא לא צריך. afilu teima Rabbi
Yoshiya l'chalek hacha lo tzarich. And maybe Rabbi יאשיה Yoshiya here will
not require you to distinguish between them. That is Rabbi יאשיה Yoshiya
who learns it from some specific quality of this פסוק pasuk will
not require you to be specific about the word יחדיו. yachdav. So
הכא לא צריך hacha lo tzarich why? מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? סברא
הוא, Sevara hu, because it only makes sense in this case. In
this case that is the case of the liabilities of a שומר
שכר. shomer sachar. Okay, so מה לי קטלה כולה מה לי קטלה
פלגא. mah li katla kula mah li katla palga. What's the difference
between killing part of the animal, that is שבורה, shvurah, the animal
was injured, or מיתה, meitah, if the animal died. Because the two
should be more or less similar. We see this in a number
of cases, the גמרא Gemara uses a phrase מה לי קטלה כולה
מה לי קטלה פלגא, mah li katla kula mah li katla palga,
what's the difference between killing part of the animal and killing the
whole animal?
That is to say, it should be the same liability, it's the
same kind of process, it's the same kind of owner. We're on
the top of צ"ה עמוד א. tzadik hey amud alef. ness or
the same kind of negligence involved. Okay.
So גניבה ואבידה בשואל מנלן? gneiva ve'aveida bishoel minalan? So how do
we know that in a case that a שואל shoel on the
one hand should be liable in a case of גניבה ואבידה gneiva
ve'aveida if the object or the animal was stolen or was lost,
but at the same time if the owner was there, the שואל
shoel should be exempt, or perhaps maybe not exempt, we're going to
see. So גניבה ואבידה gneiva ve'aveida בשואל bishoel מנלן? minalan? אי תימא
נילף משבורה ומתה, ei teima neilef mishvura u'meta, maybe we could learn
it from the fact that a שואל shoel is exempt in a
case of שבורה ומתה, shvura u'meta, if the animal was injured or
died and the owner was there, but if the owner was not
there working with them, then he would be liable. מה לשבורה ומתה
דלא אפשר למטרח ולאתויי. ma lishvura u'meta delo efshar lemitrach vela'atuyei.
So in a case of שבורה ומתה, shvura u'meta, if the animal
was injured or died, the owner can't do anything about it. There's
nothing, no additional work that he could put in to save the
animal. תאמר בגניבה ואבידה דאפשר למטרח ולאתויי, tomar begneiva ve'aveida de'efshar lemitrach
vela'atuyei,
but in a case of גניבה ואבידה, gneiva ve'aveida, if the animal
was either stolen or got lost, you could work harder and return
it. You could go find it, you could go get it back
from the thief. And therefore those two kinds of liabilities are actually
very different. אלא כי הא דתניא דנשברה ומת, ela ki ha detanya
denishbera umet, אין לי אלא שבורה ומתה. ein li ela shvura u'meta.
So, and that, but what about the fact that the ברייתא braita
seems to equate them? This ברייתא braita says, דנשברה ומת, denishbera umet,
if it was injured or died, אין לי אלא שבורה ומתה, ein
li ela shvura u'meta, that only comes to include if it was
injured or died. גניבה ואבידה מנלן? gneiva ve'aveida minalan? How do we
know it to also include the liabilities for if it was stolen
or lost in the liabilities of a שואל? shoel? So, אמרת קל
וחומר. amarta kal vachomer. So you make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
מה שומר שכר שפטור משבורה ומתה. ma shomer sachar shepatur mishvura u'meta.
So שומר שכר, shomer sachar,
a hired guardian, is exempt in the case of if the animal
was injured or died but a שואל shoel we're saying will be
liable nonetheless.
But a שומר שכר shomer sachar who is exempt in such a
case, חייב בגניבה ואבידה, chayav begneiva ve'aveida, is nonetheless liable in a
case if the animal was stolen or got lost. שואל שחייב בשבורה
ומתה, shoel shechayav bishvura u'meta,
but a שואל, shoel, a borrower, who is liable if the animal
was injured or died, אינו דין שחייב בגניבה ואבידה, eino din shechayav
begneiva ve'aveida, shouldn't he be liable for even higher standard and therefore
even if the animal was stolen or lost would also be liable?
וזהו קל וחומר שאין עליו תשובה, vezehu kal vachomer she'ein alav tshuva,
and that's a really good קל וחומר kal vachomer that you can't
ask any questions about. So if you have to say that, it
means of course you could have asked a question about it, because
if it was such a good קל וחומר kal vachomer that you
couldn't ask any questions, you wouldn't have to tell me. So מאי
אין עליו תשובה? mai ein alav tshuva? What does it mean that
there are no questions you could ask? דכי תימא איכא למפרך מה
לשומר שכר שכן משלם תשלומי כפל בטוען טענת לסטים מזויין אפילו הכי
קרנא דשואל עדיפא. de'chi teima ika lemifrach ma lishomer sachar sheken meshalem
tashlumei kefel betoen ta'anat listim mezuyyan afilu hachi karna deshoel adifa.
Because you might have thought that you could have said well, I
mean come on, שומר שכר shomer sachar in a certain case could
end up paying כפל kefel because a שומר שכר shomer sachar in
a case of טוען טענת לסטים מזויין, toen ta'anat listim mezuyyan, if
a person claims they were held up by an armed robber, even
a שומר שכר shomer sachar because an armed robber is considered like
an אונס ones and therefore the שומר שכר shomer sachar would be
off the hook. And that claim if he was then proven wrong,
well maybe you'll say that in that case if you're proven wrong
in a case where you try to claim it was stolen, then
it makes you like the thief, you have to pay כפל. kefel.
We learned that in בבא קמא Bava Kamma in great extent. And
therefore in such a case שומר שכר shomer sachar could be liable
to pay כפל, kefel, but a שואל shoel will never be able
to get himself into a situation where he's חייב chayav to pay
כפל. kefel. Why? Because there's no claim that a שואל shoel can
make to exempt himself, therefore being proven to be lying in such
a case could never get him כפל. kefel. So the only kinds
of things that you would get כפל kefel for in this case
as a שומר shomer is if you made a claim that it
was stolen and then you were proven wrong, then you're liable. That's
the only way you could get כפל. kefel. So only somebody who
could be proven to have the exemption of if it was stolen
is someone who could end up being חייב chayav in כפל. kefel.
And therefore a שואל shoel could never be חייב chayav in כפל.
kefel. And nonetheless the גמרא Gemara says yeah, even if you want
to make that claim, אפילו הכי קרנא דשואל עדיפא. afilu hachi karna
deshoel adifa. The liabilities even on the principal value of the deposit
or of the borrowed object is עדיפא, adifa, is a better, higher
threshold of liability for a שואל shoel even though he could never
get himself into a situation of paying כפל. kefel. Why? Like I
just said, because to be able to pay כפל, kefel, a שומר
shomer is putting himself into a situation where he could be exempted
by a certain claim. So the ability to pay כפל kefel is
also indicative of the fact that the שומר shomer had an out,
had a way to get out of the liability. The שואל, shoel,
even though he never pays כפל, kefel, he only pays the principal
value, only a hundred percent, not two hundred percent, nonetheless קרנא דשואל
עדיפא karna deshoel adifa because he has no
exemptions, or really very few exemptions. Okay.
Why? Why can't the שואל Shoel ever be liable for, I know
you were explaining it, but I don't see the difference between him
and a and a שומר שכר? Shomer Sachar?
Because the שואל Shoel in a case where it was stolen by
armed robbers or שבורה ומתה Shevurah umetah if it was injured or
died or any kind of אונס, Ones, right, the שואל Shoel is
still liable. The שואל Shoel is liable for all things except for
two: מתה מחמת מלאכה Metah machmat melacha if it dies while he's
working under normal normal operating procedures or בעליו עמו Baalav imo the
owner is there working with him, which is the main topic that
we're discussing here. But the point is neither of those will be
a case where it was stolen, and in order to be חייב
Chayav in כפל, Kofel, the שומר Shomer has to claim that it
was stolen and then be proven to have been claiming falsely that
it was not in fact stolen.
But he could make that could happen to the שואל, Shoel, that's
what's- But he wouldn't be exempt.
If it was stolen from him, he says it was stolen, so
you say, okay, pay, you're a שואל, Shoel, you have a high
level of liability. So he has no exemption to exploit himself. Right,
okay. איבעית אימא Iba’is eima alternatively, a different explanation for why you
couldn't make this claim. קסבר ליסטים מזוין גזלן הוא. Kasvar listim mezuyan
gazlan hu. Maybe a ליסטים מזוין Listim mezuyan an armed robber is
not a גנב Ganav that would create this liability for כפל. Kofel.
Rather, we should understand ליסטים מזוין Listim mezuyan as a גזלן Gazlan
as a different as a robber rather than a thief, and that
was an extensive debate we saw in בבא קמא Bava Kamma and
other places, many different places across ש"ס. Shas. That מחלוקת, Machlokes, I
think it's מחלוקת תנאים Machlokes tannaim maybe. Okay. אשכחן לחיוב Ashkachan lachiyuv
so we saw that it could be used to obligate someone, that
is what? The claim that שבורה ומתה Shevurah umetah the case where
the animal died will make the שואל Shoel liable.
לפטור מנלן? Liftor minalan? How do we know that if the owner
is there with the שואל Shoel that if the animal dies or
was injured, then בעליו עמו Baalav imo the owner being there can
provide an exemption even in the case where the animal died or
was injured, not only for some other liability. מנלן? Minalan? How do
we learn that? וכי תימא נילף משבורה ומתה? V’chi teima neilaf mishevurah
umetah? We could learn it from the fact that if the case
of the animal was injured or died. מה לשבורה ומתה שכן אונס?
Mah lishevurah umetah shekein ones? So just like שבורה ומתה Shevurah umetah
if the animal was injured or died is an totally unpreventable אונס,
Ones, a catastrophic event. אלא גמר משומר שכר. Ela gamar mishomer sachar.
But we could learn it from שומר שכר. Shomer Sachar. So שומר
שכר גופיה מנלן? Shomer Sachar gufay minalan? But how do we ever
learn שומר שכר Shomer Sachar that שומר שכר Shomer Sachar is liable
to pay if the animal- sorry, that שומר שכר Shomer Sachar is
exempt for if the animal was injured or died? גמירי חיובי דשומר
שכר מחיובי דשואל. Gemiri chiyuvei deshomer sachar mechiyuvei deshoel. But we learn
the liability of the שומר שכר Shomer Sachar from the שואל. Shoel.
So how do we learn it? Basically we're trying to say the
exemption from שואל Shoel we learn by way of going through the
שומר שכר. Shomer Sachar. So we'll see. So מה להלן בבעלים פטור.
Mah lehalan b’baalim patur. So just like in a case of שואל
Shoel where if the owner is there then there's an exemption, the
שואל Shoel will not have to pay. אף כאן בבעלים פטור. Af
kan b’baalim patur. So too here, that is here, not in the
case of שבורה ומתה Shevurah umetah but in a case of
just
any kind of אונס Ones but בעליו עמו Baalav imo the owners
are there, then the שואל Shoel will be exempt. ומאי גמר? U’mai
gamar? So what do we learn? אי במה מצינו? Ei b’mah matzinu?
So are we learning it from מה מצינו, Mah matzinu, מה מצינו,
Mah matzinu, just any kind of correlation between the two cases, between
שומר שכר Shomer Sachar and שואל? Shoel? איכא למפרך. Ika lemafrach. We
could challenge that מה מצינו. Mah matzinu. We could challenge the correlation
what? הכי קא פרכינן שכן אונס. Heichi ka parchinan shekein ones. But
אונס Ones is something different, that is the different the case is
only a case of אונס Ones and therefore a case where it
wasn't אונס Ones would not have an exemption. אלא אמר קרא. Ela
amar kra. No, it's explicit- not explicit in the פסוק, Pasuk, but
it's learned out from specific details in the פסוק. Pasuk. וכי ישאל,
V’chi yishal, if a person borrows something and they use the word
ו'. Vav. וכי ישאל. V’chi yishal. ו' מוסיף על עניין ראשון וילמד
עליון מתחתון. Vav mosif al inyan rishon v’yilmad elyon mitachton. We can
learn the upper case, that is שומר שכר, Shomer Sachar, from the
lower case, from שואל. Shoel. ואכתי שואל משומר שכר לא גמר. V’achti
shoel mishomer sachar lo gamar. But we can't learn שואל Shoel back
down from שומר שכר. Shomer Sachar. Why? דאיכא למפרך. D’ika lemafrach. We
could challenge that equation. מה לשומר שכר שכן פטור בשבורה ומתה Mah
lishomer sachar shekein patur b’shevurah umetah because a שומר שכר Shomer Sachar
is exempt in a case where the animal was injured or died.
תאמר בשואל שחייב בשבורה ומתה? Tomar b’shoel shechayav b’shevurah umetah? Can we
equate them? Because a שואל Shoel has much higher liability if the
animal was injured or died, a שומר שכר Shomer Sachar will be
exempt and a שואל Shoel will be liable. אלא גניבה ואבידה בשואל
חיובי מנלן? Ela gneivah va’aveidah b’shoel chiyuvey minalan? So and how do
we learn rather, so that line of reasoning was somewhat rejected, and
how do we even learn that a שואל Shoel should be liable
if something was- if the animal was stolen or got lost, which
is a much lower level of liability?
Exactly, isn't that a peculiar question? In other words, if he's liable
for an act of God, wouldn't you logically simply assume that for
human intervention he would be liable?
Well, so that's why, so מנלן דגמר משומר שכר, Minalan d’gamar mishomer
sachar, so we could learn it from
שומר שכר. Shomer Sachar. which is exactly what we're trying to do.
The principle of דיו. dayo. When you make an equation of that
sort, either by קל וחומר kal v'chomer usually, in some other דרשות
drashot as well, maybe in this case the היקש hekesh that we're
seeing here equating the two cases, so דיו dayo comes to say
you can't overreach. We saw a whole דף daf expended to discuss
the principle of דיו dayo in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. So דיו
לבוא מן הדין להיות כנידון. dayo lavo min hadin lihyot k'nidon. Whatever
is learned out by the דרשה, drasha, whatever is the predicate of
the דרשה drasha has to be like the נידון, nidon, has to
be like the test case, the example case. So מה גניבה ואבידה
בשומר שכר בבעלים פטור, ma gneivah v'aveidah b'shomer sachar b'bealim patur,
so just like for if something which was גניבה ואבידה, gneivah v'aveidah,
the animal was stolen or got lost even for a שומר שכר
shomer sachar who's normally liable for those but in a case of
בבעלים b'bealim if the owner is there with the שומר שכר shomer
sachar then פטור, patur, the שומר שכר shomer sachar will not be
liable because the owner is there, so אף גניבה ואבידה שואל נמי
בבעלים פטור. af gneivah v'aveidah shoel nami b'bealim patur.
So too a שואל, shoel, the fact that the owner is there
even for something as low level negligence as גניבה ואבידה, gneivah v'aveidah,
nonetheless if the owner is there then the שומר shomer will be
exempt. So too if the owner is there the שואל shoel will
be exempted as well.
And if the owner is there with the שואל shoel and it's
an act of God? Yeah, also פטור. patur.
That's what we saw, right? מיתה שבורה ומתה, mitah shvurah u'metah, the
animal was injured, לסטים מזויין, listim m'zuyan, right? All of these cases.
So what we're trying to get to is the point that בעליו
עמו, ba'alav imo, the owner being there, exempts the שואל shoel basically
no matter what, which is strange because שואל shoel has very high
liability. We're going to see on עמוד ב Amud Bet that רב
המנונא Rav Hamnuna tries to limit it to a very specific kind
of case and רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna himself is going to end
up being rejected. So the point is that בעליו עמו, ba'alav imo,
the owner being there, is a very far-reaching exemption for the שואל
shoel and therefore it's basically one of the only two exemptions the
שואל shoel has, but it could be very far-reaching. As long as
the owner is there, I mean most cases you borrow something the
owner isn't there, but if the owner is there then you're exempt
from any liability. Becomes interesting question things like, you know, it's
the שואל shoel if he's a poor guy what he can do
to him?
What can he do to him? You can't take him to court
for it because if the owner is there so that's a good
protection for the שואל, shoel, right?
And you see
the שואל shoel is a poor
poor
guy?
Maybe he's not a poor guy, maybe he's a rich guy.
I mean the rich שואלים. shoalim.
All we have to know is we have to, you know, I
learned this in sixth grade you have to say you have to
check your heart at the door sometimes, right? The תורה Torah tells
us that it's the same הלכה halacha for rich people and poor
people. We have to make sure, you know, it has to be
impartial as much as as much as we have to have compassion
for for the- so look, the שואל shoel whatever the liabilities the
שואל shoel got himself into he agreed to it coming into the
agreement. If he needs something more flexible he can talk to the
owner and they can work something out. Okay, so הניחא למאן דאית
ליה דיו. hanicha l'man d'it lei dayo. So that works according to
the אמורא Amora or the תנא Tanna I forget now who it
was, the opinion that holds that we do say דיו, dayo, that
is we do limit when we make a דרשה, drasha, we limit
whatever was learned out from the original case. אלא למאן דלית ליה
דיו, ela l'man d'leit lei dayo, but there are those who don't
hold of the principle of דיו, dayo, they don't have דיו. dayo.
So what do they say? מה איכא למימר? mai ika l'meimar? So
what can you say? אמר קרא וכי ישאל, amar kra v'chi yishal,
ו vav מוסיף על עניין ראשון וילמד עליון מתחתון ותחתון מעליון. mosif
al inyan rishon v'yilamed elyon mi'tachton v'tachton me'elyon. So we can learn
it from the ו. vav. The ו vav of וכי ישאל v'chi
yishal that the person borrows something will teach us מוסיף על עניין
ראשון, mosif al inyan rishon,
it continues the previous statement, I mean it makes perfect sense. The
ו vav is a conjunction between the previous paragraph and the continuing
paragraph. וילמד עליון מתחתון, v'yilamed elyon mi'tachton, we can learn the upper
case from the lower case, that is we can learn something about
שומר שכר shomer sachar from a שואל, shoel, and we can learn
something about שואל shoel from שומר שכר. shomer sachar. So איתמר פשיעה
בבעלים. itmar pshiah b'bealim. What about פשיעה בבעלים? pshiah b'bealim? What if
you were totally totally negligent and the owner is there? Does that
get you off the hook? So פליגי בה רב אחא ורבינא. pligi
bah Rav Acha u'Ravina. So it's a מחלוקת אמוראים machloket Amoraim רב
אחא ורבינא. Rav Acha u'Ravina. חד אמר חייב וחד אמר פטור.
chad amar chayav v'chad
amar patur. Because one is going to say פטור patur because the
exemption of בעליו עמו ba'alav imo should apply across the board and
one is going to say חייב, chayav, why? Because we can't extend
the principle of בעליו עמו ba'alav imo two steps removed. Why? פשיעה
pshiah negligence is something that even a שומר חינם shomer chinam is
liable for and that's two steps removed from שואל shoel because in
the תורה Torah it goes שומר חינם shomer chinam first then שומר
שכר shomer sachar and then שואל, shoel, one, two, three. And therefore
so let's see.
So איתמר פשיעה בבעלים פליגי בה רב אחא ורבינא חד אמר חייב
וחד אמר פטור. itmar pshiah b'bealim pligi bah Rav Acha u'Ravina chad
amar chayav v'chad amar patur. מאן דאמר חייב סבר מקרא נדרש לפניו.
man d'amar chayav savar mikra nidrash l'fanav. but not לפני פניו l'fne
fanav two steps removed. You can't learn two steps removed. הלכך אם
בעליו עמו השומר חנם לא כתיב. hilchach im ba'alav imo hashomer chinam
lo ktiv.
And בעליו עמו, ba'alav imo, the exemption of בעליו עמו ba'alav imo
does not apply to a שומר חנם shomer chinam according to that
position. ופשיעה נמי בשומר שכר ובשואל לא כתיב. u'peshia nami b'shomer sachar
u'v'shoel lo ktiv.
And פשיעה peshia is not mentioned explicitly in the תורה Torah as
something that you would be liable for as a שומר שכר shomer
sachar or a שואל. shoel. הלכך בשומר שכר ובשואל לחיוב אתיא בקל
וחומר משומר חנם. hilchach b'shomer sachar u'v'shoel l'chiyuv atya b'kal v'chomer mishomer
chinam.
And therefore we learn the liability of פשיעה peshia only by a
קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, not by mentioned explicit in the פסוק, pasuk,
and therefore since it's learned from קל וחומר kal v'chomer and since
we cannot extend the exemption of בעליו עמו ba'alav imo back to
שומר חנם, shomer chinam, the liabilities of a שומר חנם shomer chinam
will not fall into the category of what gets exempted by בעליו
עמו. ba'alav imo. אבל בבעלים לפטור אף בשומר שכר ובשואל לא. aval
b'baalim l'fatur af b'shomer sachar u'v'shoel lo.
And that's why פשיעה בבעלים peshia b'baalim will not... will be חייב.
chayav. That is, if you were negligent and the owner was there,
you're still liable because פשיעה peshia is something that we learn from
שומר חנם. shomer chinam. שומר חנם shomer chinam is something that we
can't learn בעליו עמו ba'alav imo to apply to and therefore you
don't get off the hook. מאי טעמא דכתיב אם בעליו עמו לשלם
השואל והשומר שכר. mai ta'ama d'ktiv im ba'alav imo l'shalem hashoel v'hashomer
sachar. So הנך חיובא דכתיב בהו בהדיא הוא דמיפטר
בהדיא.
hanach chiyuva d'ktiv behu b'hedya hu
d'miftar b'hedya. So
that's what we said now, which is that the fact that it
mentions בעליו עמו ba'alav imo only applies to שואל shoel and שומר
שכר shomer sachar and that makes them liable if the owner is
not there, and that's why it mentioned them explicitly and that's why
something learned from שומר חנם, shomer chinam, פשיעה, peshia, cannot be learned
to fall into the category of בעליו עמו. ba'alav imo. ומאן דאמר
פטור, u'man d'amar patur, the one who says פטור patur that בעליו
עמו ba'alav imo will exempt פשיעה, peshia, קסבר מקרא נדרש לפניו ולפני
פניו. kasavar mikra nidrash l'fanav u'l'fne fanav. He says you could learn
two steps removed. You could learn from שואל shoel to שומר שכר
shomer sachar and from שומר שכר shomer sachar to שומר חנם. shomer
chinam. וכי כתיב אם בעליו עמו אשומר חנם נמי כתיב. v'chi ktiv
im ba'alav imo ashomer chinam nami ktiv. And therefore if the owner
is there, quote unquote, is an exemption that applies even to שומר
חנם shomer chinam as well.
Okay, and that's why if בעליו עמו ba'alav imo will apply to
שומר חנם shomer chinam as well, then שומר חנם's shomer chinam liability
of פשיעה peshia will fall into the category of things exempted by
בעליו עמו ba'alav imo and that would apply to all three and
therefore פשיעה בבעלים peshia b'baalim across the board would be exempt. And
that's מחלוקת אמוראים. machloket amoraim. Okay, תנן. tnan.
So the משנה, mishna, this is now a sort of shorthand version
of our משנה. mishna. We're going to see how it gets discussed.
תנן השואל פרה ושאלה בעליה עמה. tnan hashoel para v'sha'ala ba'aleha ima.
If you borrow the cow and you hired or you asked the
owner to work along with you. השואל הפרה ושכר בעליה עמה hashoel
hapara v'sachar ba'aleha ima or you borrow the cow and you hired
the owner with you. שאל בעליה או שכרן ואחר כך שאל הפרה
sha'al ba'aleha o s'charan v'achar kach sha'al hapara or you hired the
worker or you know asked him to help you and then borrowed
the cow
afterward. ומתה פטור. v'meta patur. Then you're exempt. Okay, ואילו שומר חנם
לא קתני. v'ilu shomer chinam lo katani.
But the משנה mishna doesn't mention anything about a שומר חנם. shomer
chinam. The cases in the משנה mishna are either שואל shoel or
שוכר. socher. You either hired it, you paid for it, or you
borrowed it without paying, שואל. shoel. But those two cases are the
only cases mentioned in the משנה, mishna, but not שומר חנם. shomer
chinam. ולטעמך שומר שכר מי קתני? u'l'ta'amach shomer sachar mi katani?
But it doesn't mention שומר שכר shomer sachar either. אלא תנא מילתא
דכתיב בהדיא בקרא קתני. ela tana milta d'ktiv b'hedya b'kra katani.
Things which were mentioned explicitly in the תורה Torah are mentioned in
the משנה. mishna. דאתיא מדרשא לא קתני. d'atya midrash lo katani.
But things that are learned out from a דרשה drasha are not
mentioned in the משנה. mishna. Sometimes this kind of goes against principles
we have in other places. Sometimes we see that the rabbis like
to mention things in the משנה mishna that are specifically are things
they learn from דרשות. drashot. And sometimes they like to mention things
that are specifically have a better basis in the פסוקים. p'sukim. It's
kind of not so consistent rule
because we have a general sense like oh חז"ל chazal prefer things
that are from תורה שבעל פה torah shebe'al peh often because they
want to include that in the משנה. mishna. Things from תורה שבכתב,
torah shebichtav, it's in the תורה torah already, you don't have to
worry about it so much. Okay, תא שמע. ta shma. שאל ושאלה
בעליה עמה. sha'al v'sha'ala ba'aleha ima. So now kind of we're going
to analyze the משנה mishna a little bit. The משנה mishna says
שאל ושאלה בעליה עמה. sha'al v'sha'ala ba'aleha ima. You borrowed the cow
and you asked for help from the owner. שכרה ושכר בעליה עמה
s'charah v'sachar ba'aleha ima or you rented the cow and you hired
the owner to work with you. שאלה ושכר בעליה עמה sha'ala v'sachar
ba'aleha ima or kind of halfway, you borrowed the cow but you
hired the worker. שכרה s'charah or you hired the cow, you rented
the cow ושאלה בעליה עמה v'sha'ala ba'aleha ima and you asked the
owner to work with you for free. אף על פי שהבעלים עושים
מלאכה במקום אחר af al pi she'haba'alim osim melacha b'makom acher even
though the owners are doing work in some other place. somewhere else,
ומתה, v'meisa, and it dies, פטור, patur, then you're exempt, you're exempt
even though the owner is working somewhere else. So we're going to
have to analyze, what does that mean even though the owner was
working somewhere else? Because it, that means you're פטור, patur, you're exempt
because of the principle בעליו עמו, ba'alav imo, the owner is with
you, but it means with you doing the job, not with you
in the same place. So let's see. סברא הא מני רבי יהודה
היא. svara ha mani Rabbi Yehuda hi. It sounds like that's Rabbi
Yehuda's position. דאמר שוכר כשומר שכר דמי. d'amar socher k'shomer sachar dami.
Rabbi Yehuda is the one who equates a שוכר, socher, a renter,
with a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, someone who's paid to watch something.
Now that's very interesting. A שוכר, socher, what? I'm paid to use
your cow to be able to use it, but I would have
the same liability as a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, that is you
paid me to watch your cow. Okay, two very different cases. One
is I pay you to get to use it, שומר שכר shomer
sachar is you pay me to watch it without using it, but
they would have the same liability according to Rabbi Yehuda. והא האי
תנא קתני מילתא דאתי מדרשא, v'ha hai tanna katani milta d'ati midrasha,
and therefore the Tanna is including something that is learned out from
a דרשה, drasha, because the idea that a שוכר, socher, a renter,
is like a שומר שכר shomer sachar means the Mishnah includes the
same liability as a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, and שומר שכר shomer
sachar we saw was learned from a דרשה. drasha. ואי שומר חנם
לא קתני, v'ee shomer chinam lo katani, but it doesn't mention שומר
חנם, shomer chinam, and that would be a good proof that שומר
חנם shomer chinam doesn't have the same exemption of בעליו עמו. ba'alav
imo. Okay, הא מני רבי מאיר היא, ha mani Rabbi Meir hi,
and that's Rabbi Meir. דאמר שוכר כשומר חנם דמי, d'amar socher k'shomer
chinam dami,
because Rabbi Meir thinks the liability of a שוכר, socher, of a
renter, is of a lower level liability, not like Rabbi Yehuda who
thinks like a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, but like a שומר חנם,
shomer chinam, only liable for פשיעה, peshia, but not for גניבה ואבידה
gneiva v'aveida even. So כשומר חנם דמי. k'shomer chinam dami. ותנא שומר
חנם, v'tanna shomer chinam, and then the Mishnah would be including שומר
חנם shomer chinam as well, because the Mishnah includes the שוכר. socher.
So the Mishnah including a שוכר socher would include therefore the liabilities
of שומר חנם shomer chinam and therefore the exemption of בעליו עמו
ba'alav imo would apply to שומר חנם shomer chinam as well. והוא
הדין לשומר שכר. v'hu hadin l'shomer sachar. And then we could learn
שומר שכר shomer sachar by קל וחומר. kal vachomer. איבעית אימא, ibayis
eima, alternatively, כדמיחלף רבה בר אבוה, k'demichlaf Rabba bar Avuha, but Rabba
bar Avuha learns which of these opinions apply reversed. ותני שוכר כיצד
משלם רבי מאיר אומר כשומר שכר רבי יהודה אומר כשומר חנם. v'tani
socher keitzad m'shalem Rabbi Meir omer k'shomer sachar Rabbi Yehuda omer k'shomer
chinam.
He flips them. He thinks Rabbi Meir is the one who says
the שוכר socher is like a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, and Rabbi
Yehuda is the one who says a שוכר socher is like a
שומר חנם. shomer chinam. So either way we can say that our
Mishnah, if it's the second one, then Rabbi Meir fits nicely with
the Mishnah because Rabbi Meir is the one who says like שומר
שכר, shomer sachar, we don't have to worry about it. Alternatively, we'd
have to say the Mishnah is more like Rabbi Yehuda who would
be including שומר שכר, shomer sachar, but we don't want the Mishnah
to be including שומר חנם shomer chinam because then that would defeat
the, it would undermine the מחלוקת אמוראים machlokes Amoraim that we had
previously about whether or not the exemption would apply to שומר חנם
shomer chinam or not. So now we have Rav Hamnuna. אמר רב
המנונא. לעולם הוא חייב. amar Rav Hamnuna l'olam hu chayav, So Rav
Hamnuna is talking about a case of a שואל shoel now. To
what case does the exemption of בעליו עמו ba'alav imo that the
owner is there, to which cases of שואל shoel does that apply?
אמר רב המנונא amar Rav Hamnuna. לעולם הוא חייב, l'olam hu chayav.
a שואל shoel is always
חייב chayav עד שתהא פרה וחורש בה ad she'tehei para v'choresh ba
unless you borrowed a cow and you are plowing with it, חמור
ומחמר אחריה chamor u'mechamer achareha or you borrowed a donkey and you're
driving the donkey along, ועד שיהיו בעלים משעת שאילה עד שעת שבורה
ומתה, v'ad she'yihyu ba'alim mishe'as she'ila ad she'as shevura u'meisa, and unless
the owner was there present there with you working with you from
the time you borrowed it until the time of the injury. So
we have two requirements. Number one that the owner is there doing
the same work as you and number two that the owner is
present at that location from the time of the borrowing, very early
on in the negotiation. So אלמא קסבר בעליו עמו אכולה מילתא משמע.
alma kasavar ba'alav imo akula milta mashma. It sounds like the owner
being there applies to everything. So now Rava is going to challenge
Rav Hamnuna. מתיב רבא. maseiv Rava. Rava is going to
challenge from our Mishnah in fact. So how does he do that?
שאלה ושאלה בעליה עמה, she'ala v'sha'ala ba'aleha ima, if you borrow the
cow and you ask for help from the owner, שכרה ושכרה בעליה
עמה, sechara v'sechara ba'aleha ima, or you rented the cow and you
hired the owner,
ושכרה ושאלה בעליה עמה v'sechara v'sha'ala ba'aleha ima שאלה ושכרה בעליה עמה
she'ala v'sechara ba'aleha ima or the half cases, you rented the cow
and you asked the owner for help or you borrowed the cow
and you hired the worker, אף על פי שהבעלים עושים מלאכה במקום
אחר ומתה פטור. af al pi she'haba'alim osim melacha b'makom acher u'meisa
patur. Our Mishnah says as long, even if the owner is doing
work somewhere else and the animal dies, you're פטור, patur, you're exempt.
מאי לאו במלאכה אחרת? mai lav b'melacha acheres? Is it not, does
it mean he's doing another kind of work? לא באותה מלאכה. lo
b'osa melacha. It must mean he's doing the same work, the same
job, but somewhere else. אלא מאי מקום אחר? ela mai makom acher?
What does it mean in another place? דקא מרפי ואזיל קמה. d'ka
marpei v'azil kama. No, he's softening the earth in front of the
animal doing the plowing. The donkey is pulling the plow and in
front the owner of the donkey who... who's been now hired to
work by the person who borrowed the donkey, is taking the shovel
and jabbing it into the ground to soften up the dirt.
So במקום אחר be-makom acher
means not right next to the שוכר, socher, right? But doing the
exact same thing, but doing a different action that's part of the
job. Correct.
Two
feet ahead of him.
Right. Or maybe, you know, ten feet ahead or something. והא מדסיפא
על גבה, ve-ha mid-seifa al gabbah, and the fact that the סיפא
seifa case, where you're חייב chayyav is על גבה—sorry, al gabbah the—that
you're פטור patur is על גבה—he's al gabbah right there. הוי רישא
במלאכה אחרת, havei reisha be-melachah acheret, דקתני סיפא שאלה ואחר כך שכר
הבעלים de-katani seifa she'alah ve-achar kach sachar ha-ba'alim ואחר כך שכר בעלים.
ve-achar kach sachar ba'alim. The סיפא seifa is a case where you
borrow the animal first and then you hire the worker afterward. אף
על פי שהבעלים חורשים על גבה, aph al pi she-ha-ba'alim chorshim al
gabbah, even though the owner is plowing right there next to the
cow. על גבה, al gabbah, right next to it or really, you
know, right next to the animal. ומתה ve-metah and the animal dies,
חייב. chayyav. In that case the שואל sho'el would be חייב. chayyav.
אמרי רישא וסיפא באותה מלאכה. amri reisha ve-seifa be-otah melachah. So obviously
the רישא reisha and the סיפא seifa are both talking about the
same action, the same type of
labor. ברישא לרבותא קמשמע לן, be-reisha le-rabuta ka mashma lan, וסיפא לרבותא
קמשמע לן. ve-seifa le-rabuta ka mashma lan. And the סיפא seifa comes
to teach us something. So רישא לרבותא קמשמע לן, reisha le-rabuta ka
mashma lan, the רישא reisha teaches us what? דאף גב דלאו על
גבה, de-aph gav de-lav al gabbah, even though he's not exactly next
to the animal. אלא באותה מלאכה, ella be-otah melachah, but he's still
doing more or less the same type of work. כיון דהוה בעלים
בשעת שאלה, keivan de-hava ba'alim be-sha'at she'elah, because the owner was there
from the time the animal was borrowed, פטור, patur, then the שואל
sho'el would be exempt. וסיפא לרבותא קמשמע לן דאף גב דעל גבה.
ve-seifa le-rabuta ka mashma lan de-aph gav de-al gabbah. The סיפא seifa
comes to teach even though he's right there next to the animal.
כיון דלא הוה בעלים בשעת שאלה, keivan de-lo hava ba'alim be-sha'at she'elah,
since the owner was not there at the time the borrowing agreement
took place, חייב. chayyav. Then the שואל sho'el will be חייב. chayyav.
So the important ingredient is not so much that the owner be
right there next to the animal. The exemption comes from the fact
that the borrower and the owner were were present at the initial
agreement, he was there from that time.
So yeah, what's, I have a question. Sure. What's the underlying assumption
behind בעליו עמו? ba'alav immo? In other words, it's like I paid.
It's a מחלוקת. machlokes. Or maybe you just borrowed it.
Right, or I borrowed, but in other words, if you're the owner
and you're there. Right. You get all these different... what's the concept?
The concept is really, it's not really mine and the owner, the
real owner, so to speak, is there and that somehow ameliorates the
implications of my liability.
Right. So three ideas. Number one, maybe it's just totally גזירת הכתוב,
gezeirat ha-katuv, it's some arbitrary exemption. That's what a lot of people
say, actually.
I don't like that.
I know you don't like that. Number two, maybe you can't, as
if you can't have two jobs at the same time. If your
job is hiring a worker, then you also cannot be a renter
of the animal. That is, I agreed to rent the animal, I
agreed to hire this laborer. But once I hire the laborer, he's
bringing his cow with him, it's kind of like I'm not really
renting the animal anymore.
That's what I was saying.
Right. That's number two. And number three is the way a שואל
sho'el acquires liability in general is as if by becoming a partial
owner in the animal. Right. When I borrow something, the reason I'm
liable is cause like I'm like the owner. Right. But if the
actual owner is there, like you were saying, then you'll be totally
exempt because the real owner is there. So my partial or quasi-ownership
doesn't really matter.
Right. So actually, if you take your second and your third explanations,
they work really nicely together in my mind.
Oh, I see them as two separate things.
I've got, right, in other words, I've got like I rented the
animal and and I'm also going to pay for or or ask
the owner to come along with me. I've got an animal and
a human being.
I can't say that I really got the animal and the human
being schlepped along. I really got the human
who brought his hammer with him.
Right, right. Which which what we've seen with אומנין ummanin and things
like that already in the previous פרק. perek. The question of workers
bringing their tools, so in a certain sense, if I'm hiring you
to do the same job with me, you brought you brought your
cow with your ox.
Right, right. Okay. And that's why if you do it in the
reverse order it doesn't work.
Right, because then the agreement was fundamentally about the cow and not
about the worker.
Oh, that's very that works well.
Right. Okay. So שאלה חייב. she'elah chayyav. So היי מאי? hai mai?
אי אמרת בשלמא רישא במלאכה אחרת וסיפא באותה מלאכה, ei amrat bishlama
reisha be-melachah acheret ve-seifa be-otah melachah, but if you're going to tell
me that the משנה mishnah distinguishes and the רישא, reisha, the first
half of the משנה mishnah is a case where it was the
same was a different job and the סיפא seifa was the same
job, היינו רבותא, hainu rabuta, that would already be teaching me a
new הלכה. halacha. That would be the inclusion. אלא אי אמרת רישא
וסיפא באותה מלאכה, ella ei amrat reisha ve-seifa be-otah melachah, but if
you're going to say the רישא reisha and the סיפא seifa are
both talking about the same action. If you tell me that the
רישא *Reisha* and the סיפא *Seifa* are both talking about the same
doing the same work, מאי רבותא *Mai rabusa*? What is the inclusion?
What is the additional detail I learn from the משנה *Mishnah*? אידי
ואידי באותה מלאכה הוי *Idi v'idi b'osah melachah havi*. They're both doing
the same job. ועוד *Ve'od*, and further, ועוד תניא *Ve'od tanya*. So
the first half we've seen so far, this is rejecting רב המנונא
Rav Hamnuna *Rav Hamnuna's* first point, because what was רב המנונא *Rav
Hamnuna's* first point was that the owner has to be doing the
exact same work at the same time. So that was already rejected.
If you look in רש"י *Rashi*, the רש"י *Rashi* on ועוד תניא
*Ve'od tanya*, תיובתא דרב המנונא בסיפא דמילתא *Tiyuvta de'Rav Hamnuna b'seifa de'milta*.
So now the second ברייתא *braitah*, or the second analysis coming through
now is רבא Rava *Rava's* proof against רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna's* second
point, because we already disproved רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna's* first point. So
the second point, ועוד תניא *Ve'od tanya*, we can learn the ברייתא
*braitah* further. ממשמע שנאמר אם בעליו עמו לא ישלם im ba'alav immo
lo yeshalem, *Mimashma shene'emar im ba'alav imo lo yeshalem*. From the fact
that it says if the owner is there he doesn't have to
pay. איני יודע שאם בעליו אין עמו שלם ישלם *Eini yodeia she'im
ba'alav ein imo shalem yeshalem*, would I not know that if the
owner isn't there I would have to pay? Obviously. אלא מה תלמוד
לומר *Ela mah talmud lomar* בעליו אין עמו *ba'alav ein imo*, if
the owner is not there, לומר לך lomar lecha, היה עמו בשעת
שאלה *lomar lach haya imo besha'at she'eilah*, if the owner was there
at the time of the borrowing, אין צריך להיות עמו בשעת שבורה
ומתה en tzarich lihyot immo bishat shevura umeta. *ein tzarich liyot imo
besha'at shevurah ve'metah*, then the owner does not need to be there
at the time of the injury or the time of the animal
death in order to exempt the borrower. As long as he was
present at the time of the borrowing. היה עמו בשעת שבורה ומתה
haya immo bishat shevura umeta, *Haya imo besha'at shevurah ve'metah*, if he
was there at the time the animal was injured, צריך להיות עמו
בשעת שאלה *tzarich liyot imo besha'at she'eilah*, but he does have to
be there at the time of שאלה *she'eilah*, that is, the fundamental
halachic crucial point according to רבא Rava. *Rava* against רב המנונא *Rav
Hamnuna* is as long as the owner was present at the time
you borrowed it, that creates the exemption of בעליו עמו ba'alav immo.
*ba'alav imo*, which is very far-reaching. Because most times you borrow something,
you're borrowing it from the owner. I can only think, imagine I
mean before cellphones or before phones, how did you ever borrow something
with the owner not there? I guess you have to go make
an agreement, you go to his house on Tuesday, say I know
you're going out of town, next week while you're away I want
to borrow your cow, and he says okay fine. And then that
would be a case where you wouldn't have the exemption. But normal
cases of borrowing something, this goes back to what you were saying
before Joe, that the שואל *shoel* would trying to see, so רבא
Rava, *Rava's* interpretation certainly gives a שואל *shoel* many more protections, because
the שואל *shoel* is going to be exempt under many normal circumstances.
Anytime you borrow something and it's coming directly from the owner, then
you're going to be exempt. Okay. ותניא אידך *Vetanya idach*, ממשמע שנאמר
בעליו אין *mimashma shene'emar ba'alav ein*...
yeah wait, what was that? I missed something before then.
So the point is that even if the owner is not there
at the time that the animal is injured. That is, I hired
him to work with me whatever, he's working with me today, tomorrow,
next week. And then I keep working with the cow after he
goes away, and then the cow dies, I'll still be exempt because
he was agreed to work with me from the time of שאלה
*she'eilah*. Right.
So as long as it was משעת שאלה *mesha'at she'eilah*, then even
at the time of the injury. So רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna* required
that the
hired labor agreement continue through from the time of the שאלה *she'eilah*,
from the time of the borrowing, all the way through until the
injury. But for רבא Rava *Rava*, he rejects רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna*,
he says as long as the agreement was in place from the
time of hire, then even later on they could split ways, he
could still keep working with the animal and the exemption would still
be in place, which makes it sound much more like it's an
arbitrary kind of distinction. If the owner is no longer there, why
should I still have the exemption? The owner isn't working with me
anymore, he was working with me at the time we made the
agreement but he's not working for me
now, still exempt. So that's a point that sort of opens up
room to say it's a very broad, very far-reaching exemption just in
terms of defining a שואל *shoel* and not actually in terms of
a sort of logical liability.
Yeah, בעליו עמו *ba'alav imo*, wait, it doesn't mean at the time
that you made the agreement, of course he was there when you
made the agreement.
No, but that he was agreed to work with him at the
time of the agreement.
Right. And he was there when you actually borrowed the cow, when
you took...
when you take the cow and start working,
he's there
and he's working for you. Right. Okay, ותניא אידך *vetanya idach*, the
ברייתא *braitah* continues, ממשמע שנאמר בעליו אין עמו שלם ישלם *mimashma shene'emar
ba'alav ein imo shalem yeshalem*, איני יודע שאם בעליו עמו לא ישלם
*eini yodeia she'im ba'alav imo lo yeshalem*? And vice-versa, if the פסוק
*pasuk* already says if the owner is not there I am liable
to pay, I couldn't figure out that if the owner is there
I wouldn't be liable? אלא מה תלמוד לומר *Ela mah talmud lomar*
אם בעליו עמו *im ba'alav imo*, if the owner is there, לומר
לך lomar lecha, כיון שיצא מרשות משאיל שעה אחת בבעלים ומתה פטור
*lomar lach keivan sheyatza mereshut mash'il sha'ah achat beba'alim vametah patur*. It
comes to teach that as soon as, once there was even a
moment where the animal had left the owner... left the רשות *reshut*,
the control of its owner into the borrower's control even for שעה
אחת *sha'ah achat*, one moment, בבעלים *beba'alim*, and the owner is there
working with you in an agreement, פטור *patur*, then you'll be exempt
if the animal dies. תיובתא דרב המנונא תיובתא *Tiyuvta de'Rav Hamnuna tiyuvta*.
And therefore רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna's* position is totally rejected. So רבא
Rava *Rava* is able to argue completely against רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna*.
Let's try to start the next סוגיא *sugya* is a little bit
challenging. We'll get a start. We're going to have אביי Abaye *Abaye*
and רבא Rava *Rava* kind of going back to something we saw
previously, the מחלוקת *machloket* between רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya, *Rabbi Yoshiya* and
רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonatan. *Rabbi Yonatan* at the bottom of דף צ"ד
עמוד ב' *daf tzadik daled amud bet*. So just remember רבי יאשיה
Rabbi Yoshiya *Rabbi Yoshiya* and רבי יונתן *Rabbi Yonatan* there had the
מחלוקת *machloket* about מקלל אביו ואמו *mekalel aviv ve'imo* and how much
when you have two cases or two criteria for the same מצוה
*mitzvah* in the תורה *Torah*, how much do both have to be
fulfilled in order to make you liable, how much one or the
other? Right? So רבי יונתן *Rabbi Yonatan*, רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya *Rabbi
Yoshiya* says מקלל אביו ואמו *mekalel aviv ve'imo*. So it says אביו
קילל *aviv kilel*, אמו קילל *imo kilel*. Each one is mentioned next
to the word קילל *kilel* to curse, and therefore רבי יאשיה *Rabbi
Yoshiya* says it comes to make you liable in one or the
other. But normally not so much. And רבי יונתן *Rabbi Yonatan* learns
it a little bit differently. And רבי יונתן *Rabbi Yonatan* says generally
unless the תורה *Torah* is explicit that it applies יחדו *yachdav* to
them both together, we normally would assume that any two criteria would
apply independently. So that was רבי יונתן *Rabbi Yonatan*. So now we're
going to see אביי Abaye, *Abaye* and רבא Rava *Rava* have a
little bit of a debate about רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya* and רבי
יונתן *Rabbi Yonatan*. Okay. אביי Abaye סבר לה כרבי יאשיה *Abaye savar
lah keRabbi Yoshiya*. אביי Abaye *Abaye* holds like רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya*
ומתרץ לקרא כרבי יאשיה *umitaretz likra keRabbi Yoshiya*. And he learns the
פסוקים *psukim*. Not only he holds like רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya*, he
also interprets the פסוקים *psukim* like רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya*. רבא Rava
סבר לה כרבי יונתן *Rava savar lah keRabbi Yonatan* ומתרץ לקרא כרבי
יונתן *umitaretz likra keRabbi Yonatan*. And רבא Rava, *Rava* holds like רבי
יונתן *Rabbi Yonatan*'s position, and he also interprets the פסוקים *psukim* like
רבי יונתן *Rabbi Yonatan*. Let's see what they say. Okay. אביי Abaye
סבר לה כרבי יאשיה *Abaye savar lah keRabbi Yoshiya*. What does it
mean that אביי Abaye *Abaye* holds like רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya* ומתרץ
לקרא כרבי יאשיה *umitaretz likra keRabbi Yoshiya*? And he reads the פסוקים
*psukim* like רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya*. בעליו אין עמו שלם ישלם *be'alav
ein imo shalem yeshalem*. So the פסוק *pasuk* says if the owner
is not there, you have to pay. טעמא דליתא בתרוייהו *ta'ama deleita
betarvaihu*. The fact that he's not there for both of them. So
הא איתא בחדא וליתא בחדא פטור *ha ita bechada veleita bechada patur*.
So the fact that the owner is not there, שלם ישלם *shalem
yeshalem*, you have to pay, but meaning תרוייהו tarvayhu, *tarvaihu*. What's תרוייהו
*tarvaihu*? תרוייהו *tarvaihu* in this case meaning not only that the פסוק
*pasuk* that, sorry, ותני אידך דף צ"ד עמוד ב' *vetani idach
daf tzadik daled amud bet*... You need both פסוקים *psukim* for the
דרשא *drasha*. That is what? That is, you need the case of
in the, and it says in רש"י *Rashi* in the second to
last line in רש"י *Rashi*, והכתיב אם בעליו עמו *veha ketiv im
be'alav imo*, the owner is there, דמשמע נמי בתרוייהו ישנו בזו וישנו
בזו ודלא משלם *demashma nami betarvaihu yeshno bezo veyeshno bezo vedelo meshaleim*.
הא איתא בחדא מניהו ומשלם *ha ita bechada mineihu umeshaleim* because the
exemption requires both. Number one, that the owner is not there, and
the owner is, sorry, that the owner be there with you and
that the owner was working with you, right? So let's see. Okay.
And those two criteria come to, both have to be there. If
you only have one, איתא בחדא וליתא בחדא פטור *ita bechada veleita
bechada patur*, then you'll be exempt. והכתיב אם בעליו עמו לא ישלם
*veha ketiv im be'alav imo lo yeshalem*. If the owner is there,
you don't have to pay. טעמא דאיתא בתרוייהו *ta'ama de'ita betarvaihu*. That's
the case where you have both. So הא איתא בחדא וליתא בחדא
מחייב mechayiv, *ha ita bechada veleita bechada mechayev*. But couldn't you then
say it oppositely? Then you're only exempt if the owner is there,
then you don't have to pay, and therefore that's if you have
both. But if you only had one and not the other, you
would be חייב chayiv, *chayav*.
What's both? What's both?
So both meaning that the owner, that both the owner and the
animal are there, as far as I understand.
Both? The two things are the owner and the animal?
Meaning why do we have both פסוקים *psukim*? Why does the פסוק
*pasuk* say אם בעליו עמו לא ישלם *im be'alav imo lo yeshalem*
and בעליו אין עמו שלם ישלם *be'alav ein imo shalem yeshalem*? Why
do we need both פסוקים *psukim*?
You should be logically, you could infer it.
Right. So if we only had one, if it only said אין
בעליו עמו *ein be'alav imo*, אין עמו שלם ישלם *ein imo shalem
yeshalem*, I would have thought, okay, then as long as he is
there, I'll be exempt. Alternatively, if I had the other way, if
it only said אם בעליו עמו לא ישלם *im be'alav imo lo
yeshalem*, then that's because I have both איתא בתרוייהו *ita betarvaihu*.
Sorry, I'm having a little hard time explaining what... Right. Both?
One or both doesn't mean one or both פסוקים *psukim*. It means
both the person and the animal.
I think so.
I'm not positive either. That's why I'm...
Oh, at both times!
I'm sorry. איתא בתרוייהו *ita betarvaihu*. That the owner is there both
at the time of the borrowing, at the hiring agreement, and at
the time when the animal dies, at the time of אונס *ones*.
Sorry.
Okay.
So according to רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya*, this is אביי
*Abaye*'s version of רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya*. That is, if I had
only the פסוק בעליו אין עמו שלם ישלם *pasuk be'alav ein imo
shalem yeshalem*, the owner is not there, then you have to pay,
I would have thought, okay, so the owner is not there at
either time. But if the owner was there either at the time
of the agreement or at the time of the death, then I
would be exempt. That's possibility number one. But if I have the
other
פסוק *pasuk*... both times at the time of the agreement, the hiring
and at the time the animal's death. איתי בתרוייהו. האי איתי בחדא
ולא איתי בחדא, ha itee bechada velo itee bechada, but if the
owner is only there at one time and not at the other,
מחייב, I would be obligated, liable. לומר לך, היה עמו בשעת שאילה,
haya immo bishat sheila, אינו צריך להיות עמו בשעת שבורה ומתה. eno
tzarich lihyot immo bishat shevura umeta. So that sounds like then that
if the owner was only working with me from the time that
we agreed on it, but not at the time the animal died,
היה עמו בשעת שבורה ומתה, haya immo bishat shevura umeta, צריך להיות
עמו בשעת שאילה. tzarich lihyot immo bishat sheila. How can you say
then that the flip, that what if the owner was only working
with me at the time the animal died but had not even
agreed to it from the previous time? And that's why
אביי reads it that way. That is, אביי, what we just saw,
the rejection of רב המנונא was from רבא himself. So אביי is
disagreeing with רבא. אביי holding like רבי יאשיה, and רבי יאשיה being
the one who sees you need to have an explicit distinction between
the two criteria. So that's why the two criteria, תרוייהו, that when
the case where the owner has to be working with the borrower
both at the time of the rental agreement and at the time
of the death of the animal, that's why, that's why אביי holds
like רבי יאשיה and not like רבי יונתן. And רבא, רבא whose
position I think we have an easier time understanding, רבא's the one
who says that we fundamentally care more about the time of the
rental agreement more than the time of the animal's death. So רבא
סבר לה כרבי יונתן ומתרץ לקרא כרבי יונתן. Rava savar lah kerabbi
yonatan umitaretz likra kerabbi yonatan. דתניא, Detanya, אם בעליו עמו לא ישלם,
if the owner is there you don't have to pay. That's exemption
of בעליו עמו. משמע דאיתי בתרוייהו, mashma de'itee betarvayhu, the owner was
there, that is, working with the borrower both at the time of
the agreement and at the time of the animal's death. משמע נמי
דכי איתי בחדא ולא איתי בחדא פטור, mashma nami dechi itee bechada
velo itee bechada patur, and you would be exempt if he was
present at either time. וכתיב בעליו אין עמו שלם ישלם, uchitiv ba'alav
en immo shalem yeshalem, but it says if the owner is not
there you are liable to pay. משמע דליתא בתרוייהו. mashma deleita betarvayhu.
משמע נמי דכי איתי בחדא ולא איתי בחדא. mashma nami dechi itee
bechada velo itee bechada. It sounds like well what about a case
where he was only working with you at one time and not
both? So it sounds like you would be חייב, that
is, they contradict. לומר לך, היה עמו בשעת שאילה, haya immo bishat
sheila, אין צריך להיות עמו בשעת שבורה ומתה. And that was רבא's
opinion. That is, רבא says as long as the owner was working
with you from the time of שאילה, sheila, the exemption will kick
in even if he's not working with you anymore at the time
the animal dies. היה עמו בשעת שבורה ומתה, צריך להיות עמו בשעת
שאילה, tzarich lihyot immo bishat sheila, and that's רבא's position. That is,
אביי says the exemption will take place if he's there at either
time, if he was agreed to be working with you either at
the time of the rental of the animal or at the time
the animal died. According to רבא, it's only if he was present
and agreed to work with you at the time of the rental,
but he doesn't have to be there at the time of the
at the time the animal died. Okay, so that's a good place
to stop for now. We'll pick up on שבת Shabbat and I
hope everyone has a wonderful ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, everyone has a
wonderful חג, Chag, everyone has a wonderful שבת Shabbat tonight and I'll
see you tomorrow afternoon after I check the time. All right, wonderful,
great day.